A Guide to the Joseph C. McDaniel Papers
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10553-p
Joseph C. McDaniel Papers 1944-1983
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10553-p
ca. 1800 items
Mrs. Joseph C. McDaniel
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the Library by Mrs. Joseph C. McDaniel of Urbana, Illinois, on January 19, 1989.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of ca. 1,800 items (6 Hollinger boxes, 2 linear feet), 1944-1945, 1953-1983, and undated, chiefly the professional correspondence, printed material, and manuscripts of Dr. Joseph C. McDaniel, the Assistant Professor of Horticulture at the University of Illinois, College of Agriculture, Urbana, Illinois.
The first series contains the office file copies of McDaniel's professional correspondence as a professor of horticulture at the University of Illinois, and is chiefly concerned with his research regarding persimmon trees, miscellaneous nut trees, magnolias, hollies, and membership in the American Magnolia Society, and the Northern Nut Growers Association.
These papers complement those of an earlier accession of McDaniel Papers (10,553-j), with a greater emphasis on his work with fruits and nuts.
The second series consists of the papers of McDaniel, including talks, articles, and research notes. Titles of most of these include:
1953 Feb The Colby, a Sub-Zero English Walnut
1963 Securing Seed Production in Magnolia Acuminata and M. Cordata
1965 Jun A New Look at Magnolias
1965 Oct 8 A Look at Variation in Sweet Bay, Its Hybrids, and Some Other Magnolias South to Guatemala
1965 Nov 6 The Cairo Magnolia
1965 Nov 8 Variations in the Sweet Bay Magnolias
1966 Fall A New-Old Magnolia Hybrid
1966 American Persimmons
1967 Jul 18 Sorting Out the Sweet Bays
1967-1968 Pecan Article for the Encyclopedia Britannica
1968 Mar 9 What Can We Do With Sweet Bay Magnolia?
1968 Magnolias and Organic Phosphate Insecticide Injury
ca. 1968 Flowering Quinces and Chinese Quince
1969 Jun 13 Sporadic Monoecism in Three Related Diospyros Virginiana Cultivars
1969 Sep 4 & Oct 4 Modern Magnolias
1969 Nov 18 Tree Nut and Persimmon Breeding
1970 Apr 5 A Cooperative Magnolia Improvement Plan
1970 Persimmon Notes
1970 Dec 31 An American-Chinese Hybrid Holly, Shin Nien
1971 Mar 2 American Persimmons, Versatile Fruits
1971 Some Unusual Red Fruited Evergreen Hollies
1972 Jul 14 Persimmons in the Midwest and Northern States
1972 Dec 21 Nut Growing in Illinois
1973 (early) Choosing Pecans and Hicans for Farther North
1973 Sep Persimmon Cultivars for Northern Areas
1973 Dec 11 Variety in Evergreen Magnolias
1973 Persimmons in the Midwest and Northern States
1973 Variety Among Magnolias
1974 Feb 13 Arnold Arboretum's `Centennial,' a New M. Stellata
1974 Mar 26 Getting More From the Thanksgiving and Christmas Cacti
1974 Aug 27 Breeding Better American Persimmons
1974 Oct A New Look at Mulberries
1974 Dec 21 Magnolia Hybrids in Section Rytidiospermum
1974 Dec 26 Hybridizing Section Rytidiospermum
ca. 1974 In Praise of Slowness
1975 Jan 6 'Chyverton Red' and Other New Magnolias from Cornwall
1975 Feb 3 Magnolias for the 21st Century -A Breeder's Outlook
1975 Feb 5 New Hybrids in Magnolia Give Reliable Spring Flower
1975 Feb 18 Persimmons: Oriental, American, and Hybrid
1975 Feb 28 A Look at Pecan Research in 1975
1975 Apr The Big Leaf Magnolia and Its Relatives
1975 May 31 Magnolia Macrophylla
1975 Jun 2 Variety, or the Confessions of a Grafter
1975 Jun 4 Persimmons for Illinois Fruit Gardens
1975 Jun 6, 19 Magnolias for the Houston Area
1975 Jun 15, 27 Magnolia Breeding Aims for the 80's
1975 Jun 16 Magnolias, Part I, the Deciduous Kinds
1975 Jun 20 The Deciduous Magnolias of West Florida
1975 Jun 24 Latin American Magnolias
1975 Jun 30 Using Hybrids in Breeding
1975 Jul Dichogamy and Productivity in the Walnut Family
1975 Jul 10 Magnolia Hybrids for the 1980's, Choosing Parents in Subgenus Yulania
1975 Jul 30 Choosing Magnolias for Illinois
1975 Sep For Magnolia Connoisseurs
1975 Nov 20 Grafting with Chip Buds
1975 Dec 9 The American Big Leaf Magnolias
1975 Dec 15 Three Big Leaf Magnolias
1976 Feb 27 Deciduous Magnolias
1976 Aug 2 What is Hardy ?
1976 Aug 6 Pecans in Midwest
1976 Sep 11 Some New Names in Magnolia Species and Hybrids
1976 Nov 2 Breeding for the 1980's and Beyond
1978 Aug 6 Preface for The International Persimmon Book
1978 Dec 13 Pecan chapter in a book about nut trees
1979 Jul 11 The Spelling of `Lileny' (A Soulangiana Cultivar)
ca. 1979 Upgrading the Propagation List for the 1980's
1979 International Hybridizations with Magnolia Sieboldii
1980 Apr 26 Windswept
1980 Dec 8 Wilson's Magnolias in America
1979 Persimmons for Everyone by Eugene and Mary E. Griffith, edited and augmented by J. C. McDaniel (3 folders)
n.d. Deciduous Hollies Brighten Landscape
n.d. Holly Notes--Unusual Species, Hybrids, and a New Handbook
n.d. A New Canker of Butternut
n.d. Cultivars of Pecans and Other Nut Trees in the Kansas Region
n.d. Recent Hybridizations with American Magnolias
n.d. Ilex Decidua
n.d. Butternut and Related Asian Species, including Heartnut, and Their Hybrids
n.d. Outline of Nut Tree Pollination
n.d. Holly Hybridization
n.d. The Gresham Cultivars
n.d. Literature of Magnoliaceae
n.d. Background for Persimmon Breeding
n.d. Magnolias Hardy in Poland
n.d. Magnolia virginiana var. australis `Henry Hicks,' a new evergreen magnolia cultivar
n.d. Upgrading Magnolia virginiana Seedling Products
n.d. Magnolias Frequently Self-Unfruitful
n.d. Spring Hardiness, or Surviving April in a Continental Climate
n.d. Variety in Evergreen Magnolias
n.d. Amelanchier Arborea
n.d. Nuts, Persimmons, and Minor Fruit Tree Varieties in Illinois
n.d. Two Amateur Breeders of Super Filberts and Walnuts
n.d. Three Magnolia Companion Plants for Shade
n.d. Persimmon Propagation for the Amateur
n.d. Polygamous Persimmons
n.d. Magnolia Society Newsletter, "Paragraphs at Large
n.d. Choosing Ornamental Magnolias for Illinois
n.d. An Illinois Nut Grove
n.d. Hardies Hybrid Hollies
n.d. Persimmon Breeding Material Source
n.d. Suggested Tree Fruit and Nut Varieties For Illinois Home Fruit Gardens
n.d. Outline of Nut Tree Pollination
n.d. What's New in Persimmons ?
n.d. A New Pecan from Illinois
n.d. Persimmon Cultivars for Northern Areas
n.d. American Persimmon, an Emerging Horticultural Crop
Container List
- Correspondence, 1944, 1955-1963; (7 folders) (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1964-1965; (7 folders) (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1966-1971; (7 folders) (Box Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1972-1982, n.d.; (6 folders) (Box Box 4)
- Miscellaneous and Printed Material, 1945, 1960-1983, n.d. (Box Box 4)
- Papers by Joseph McDaniel, 1953, 1961-1980; (6 folders) (Box Box 5)
- Persimmons for Everyone by Eugene and Mary E. Griffith, edited and augmented by J. C. McDaniel, 1979; (3 folders) (Box Box 6)
- Papers by Joseph McDaniel, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 6)
- Papers by Joseph McDaniel (Untitled), n.d. (Box Box 6)
- Papers by Joseph McDaniel (Incomplete), n.d. (Box Box 6)
- Magnolia Checklist Computer Printout Bibliographical Listing, 1975 (Box Oversize Folder)